Today is י"א Yud Aleph and we pick up with the very
top, maybe we'll start at the very bottom of י' עמוד ב'
Yud Amud Bet just to remind ourselves what the debate is and
we're going to be figuring out when the world was created, I
don't know figuring it out but anyway we'll be talking about it.
תניא, Tanya, so five lines from the bottom of י' עמוד ב',
Yud Amud Bet, we
taught, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer Omer, בתשרי נברא העולם, Be-Tishrei nivra
ha-olam, the world was created in תשרי. Tishrei. בתשרי נולדו אבות, Be-Tishrei
noldu avot, בתשרי מתו אבות, be-Tishrei metu avot, so the forefathers were
born and died on תשרי. Tishrei. בפסח נולד יצחק, Be-Pesach nolad Yitzchak,
the one thing that wasn't on תשרי Tishrei or one of the
few things was בפסח נולד יצחק be-Pesach nolad Yitzchak and we'll see
why in the גמרא Gemara but to some degree it's tied into
the next line of בראש השנה נפקדה שרה רחל וחנה. be-Rosh Hashanah
nifkeda Sarah Rachel ve-Chanah. אם שרה רחל וחנה Im Sarah Rachel ve-Chanah
were remembered and that means they became pregnant, so שרה Sarah became
pregnant on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, then we'll see why the גמרא
Gemara feels that יצחק Yitzchak had to be born on a יום
טוב, Yom Tov, but anyway to some degree that connects to him
being born on פסח Pesach although that is only about six months
later, we'll see about that. בראש השנה יצא יוסף מבית האסורים, Be-Rosh
Hashanah yatza Yosef mi-beit ha-asurim, on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah יוסף Yosef
was freed from prison. בראש השנה בטלה עבודה מאבותינו במצרים, Be-Rosh Hashanah
batlah avodah me-avoteinu be-Mitzrayim, on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah their work, they
were freed from servitude or they weren't freed, they didn't become free
people but they stopped having to work. בניסן נגאלו, Be-Nissan nigalu, the
actual redemption happens in ניסן, Nissan, so this is similar to, thank
you, this idea of a gradual freedom we pointed out parallels what
we saw about the whole idea of the movement from ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah to יום כיפור Yom Kippur on the יובל. Yovel. בניסן
נגאלו בתשרי עתידין להיגאל, Be-Nissan nigalu be-Tishrei atidin lehigael,
but in the future they'll be redeemed in תשרי. Tishrei. So pretty
much everything was in תשרי Tishrei except you have to say what
was in ניסן Nissan which was פסח Pesach and יוסף Yosef and
יצחק's Yitzchak birth. That's רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, what's his name, right.
רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, בניסן נברא העולם, be-Nissan nivra ha-olam,
בניסן נולדו אבות, be-Nissan noldu avot, בניסן מתו אבות, be-Nissan metu avot,
no no no, world was created in ניסן Nissan and the forefathers
were born in ניסן, Nissan, they died in ניסן. Nissan. בפסח נולד
יצחק, Be-Pesach nolad Yitzchak, again with this idea that יצחק Yitzchak was
born in פסח, Pesach, which then means at that point he winds
up conceding, or at one point is, בראש השנה נפקדה שרה רחל
וחנה. be-Rosh Hashanah nifkeda Sarah Rachel ve-Chanah. That idea that they were
remembered, שרה רחל וחנה, Sarah Rachel ve-Chanah, that was ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, again that could be seen as tied into the יצחק Yitzchak
idea, also tied in as the גמרא Gemara will do it to
the idea of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah as the day of remembrance.
בראש השנה יצא יוסף מבית האסורים, Be-Rosh Hashanah yatza Yosef mi-beit ha-asurim,
יוסף Yosef was freed on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. בראש השנה בטלה
עבודה מאבותינו במצרים, Be-Rosh Hashanah batlah avodah me-avoteinu be-Mitzrayim, they stopped having
to do work in מצרים Mitzrayim on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, so
these things he does concede was on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. ובניסן
נגאלו ובניסן עתידין להיגאל, U-be-Nissan nigalu u-be-Nissan atidin lehigael, they were redeemed
in ניסן Nissan and in the future they will be redeemed in
ניסן. Nissan. Okay so basic debate of whether most of these things
you date from ניסן Nissan or from תשרי. Tishrei. Now the גמרא
Gemara is going to unpack it. תניא, Tanya, we find in a
ברייתא. Braita. רבי
אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, מנין שבתשרי נברא העולם, mna'in she-be-Tishrei nivra
ha-olam, how do you know the world was created in תשרי? Tishrei?
שנאמר, She-ne'emar, ויאמר אלוהים תדשא הארץ דשא, Vayomer Elohim tadshe ha-aretz deshe,
God says let the land be covered with grass, עשב מזריע זרע,
esev mazria zera, grass with seed, עץ פרי עושה פרי, etz peri
oseh peri, a fruit tree making fruit. איזו חודש, Eizu chodesh, what
is the month שהארץ מוציאה דשאים ואילן מלא פירות, she-ha-aretz motzia deshaim
ve-ilan maleh perot, that the land brings forth grass and the tree
is filled with fruit? הוי אומר זה תשרי, Hevei omer zeh Tishrei,
it's תשרי. Tishrei. You know think about it, like when's apple picking
season, right? It's in September, that's when the trees are filled with
fruit is in the beginning of the fall. In the Northern Hemisphere
here, right, what if it's so in the Mediterranean?
Well that's the Northern Hemisphere, yeah. But grass grows in the spring
though.
Okay so here's the question about the grass part of the story.
The גמרא Gemara is going to focus on the tree and going
to focus on the difference of whether the tree is filled with
fruit, which is what it is in the fall in September in
תשרי, Tishrei, or whether it starts blossoming and the fruit starts coming
out, which is what happens in spring and in ניסן. Nissan. That's
what the גמרא Gemara will focus on. רש"י Rashi says that there's
also an issue going on here about the grass although the גמרא
Gemara doesn't focus on it and then there's a question of the
גרסא. girsa. Our גרסא girsa is מוציאה דשאים motzia deshaim which is
that this is the time when the grass starts coming out.
רש"י Rashi seems to have had the גרסא girsa here מלאה דשאים,
mele'ah desha'im, that all the grass has already grown. I don't know,
when is it grassier in the spring or in the fall?
Spring.
In the Mediterranean it's the spring, yeah, because nothing grows in the
fall because it's dry.
Aha, so there's a question here, yeah,
the ארץ מוציאה דשאים aretz motzia deshaim which implies when it sprouts.
Right, when it sprouts.
In the fall you've still got the grass. Sprouting of the grass
in the spring?
Right, so that's why some have the גרסא, girsa, so it seems
that רש"י Rashi had the גרסא girsa and this is going to
be contrasted to a פסוק pasuk which is ותוצא הארץ דשא, vatotzei
ha-aretz deshe, which was when it starts coming out. So here רש"י's
Rashi גרסא girsa seems to have been, which is what the ב"ח
Bach changes it to, it's תדשא הארץ, tadshe ha-aretz, תדשא tadshe means
already a coating of
grass. the grass at all. The emphasis here is whether what the
story is with the trees, the way trees are different in the
fall or in the spring. Let's read it with the switch in
the גרסא *girsa* which seems to reflect רש"י's Rashi *Rashi's* גרסא
*girsa*
of מלאה דשאים *Melei'a Deshaim*.
Well, it's implicit. If you look at the רש"י Rashi *Rashi* where
he says תדשא הארץ תתכסה ותתלבש בדשאים *Tadshei Ha'aretz titkaseh vetitlabesh bideshaim*,
and then if you skip down
to four lines down, we have to, you have to read it
in conjunction with the next piece of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* where
it says ותוצא ולא כתיב ktiv, ותדשא *Vetotzei velo ksiv vetadshe*. Anyway,
if you combine it, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* isn't explicit, but the ב"ח
*Bach* is picking up on the hints in רש"י Rashi *Rashi*. Okay,
so we'll read it with the ב"ח's *Bach's* גרסא
*girsa*. That in the Mediterranean there's no grass,
or you're aware of the Southern Hemisphere.
Oh, that I don't know.
Right. But presumably if this was right this, you know, if גן
עדן *Gan Eden* was around, I mean I don't know if this
was happening in גן עדן *Gan Eden*, I mean presumably in the
whole world, you know. It's an interesting question, that's right. But it,
if you focus on the גן עדן *Gan Eden* area which is
presumably, you know, the fertile crescent, right, the Euphrates and the Tigris
and so on, so we're still talking about the Northern Hemisphere.
Yeah, I get the impression that in the Kabbalistic period or Hasidic
period, there was this idea about
that.
Really? You could be right. I don't know all the different ideas
about גן עדן *Gan Eden*. Certainly the פשט *pshat* of the פסוקים
pesukim *psukim* is that גן עדן *Gan Eden* is in the fertile
crescent. But of course this is about the world, you know. So
it's also, it's a good point trying to identify what's happening in,
I'm just guessing, trying to identify what time of year this is
happening if it's happening in the entire world. So that's a good
point, the difference between the hemispheres. Although you're right, I don't know
if the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* did know the difference between the, you
know, between the hemispheres. Anyway, all right, so we're going to read
it מלאה *melei'a*. So תדשא *tadshe* means it's already coated with grass,
and the emphasis is going to be on עץ פרי etz pri?
*etz pri*. It's already fully a fruit tree. So it's filled with
grass and filled with fruit. What time is it? רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* says it's תשרי Tishrei *Tishrei*. It's תשרי Tishrei? *Tishrei*.
ואותו הפרק זמן רביעה היתה *Ve'oto haperak zman revia hayta*, and that
was the time of rain, right, the rains you want the rains
to begin like soon after תשרי Tishrei? *Tishrei* in חשוון Cheshvan. *Cheshvan*.
וירדו גשמים וצמחו *Veyeirdu geshamim vetzamchu*, and the rain came down and
they were and the grass sprouted up, or the or whatever everything
sprouted. שנאמר Shene'emar ואד יעלה מן הארץ והשקה את כל פני האדמה
*Shene'emar ve'ed ya'aleh min ha'aretz vehishka et kol pnei ha'adama*, right, the
beginning in פרק ב' *Perek Bet* of בראשית Bereishit, *Bereshit* where, where
in the where this the clouds cause the rain and ultimately part
of the story with the creation of the human being. So the
beginning of the rainy season happens soon after תשרי Tishrei. *Tishrei*. Why
we start saying ותן טל ומטר *v'ten tal umatar* and משיב הרוח
ומוריד הגשם *mashiv haruach umorid hagashem* and so on.
I never understood this. Why is the word for a quarter, a
fourth, the same as the word for rain?
I don't think it's the word for a fourth. It's I think
it's the word for sexual relations, רובע *rove'a*. To water.
Right, because it's, you know, the whole thing is a very much
sort of a sexually suggestive and the you know the שדה הבעל
*Sdeh HaBa'al* and the rain comes down and it fertilizes the earth
and something sprouts forth, right, it penetrates the earth. So the word,
you know, to be רובע בהמה *rove'a behema*, right, whatever, and לרובע
*larove'a*. Right. Yeah, yeah. So it's not from a quarter. It's, it's
really from a sexual term. Fertility image. Yes, exactly. All right, where
were we? Okay. ותוצא הארץ דשא *Vetotzei ha'aretz deshe* for פשט *pshat*
רביעה ראשונה *revia rishona*. ותוצא הארץ דשא *Vetotzei ha'aretz deshe*. Okay. רבי
יהושע אומר Rabbi Yehoshua omer: מנין שבניסן נברא העולם *Rabbi Yehoshua omer
minayin shebenisan nivra ha'olam*? How do you know it was created in
ניסן Nisan. *Nissan*? שנאמר Shene'emar, *Shene'emar*, the verse says ותוצא הארץ דשא
עשב מזריע זרע ועץ עשה פרי oseh pri *Vetotzei ha'aretz deshe eisev
mazria zera ve'etz oseh pri*. So it's not yet a fruit tree,
it's not yet filled with fruit, it's a tree that is making
fruit or will make fruit. איזהו חודש שהארץ *Eizehu chodesh sheha'aretz*, again
we'll go with the ב"ח's *Bach's* גרסא *girsa*, מוציאה דשאים *motzia deshaim*,
and ותוצא הארץ דשא *Vetotzei ha'aretz deshe*. It's not yet coated with
grass, it's just initially sprouting grass. ואילן מוציא פירות *Ve'ilan motzi peirot*,
and it's not yet an עץ פרי etz pri *etz pri*, it's
an עץ עשה פרי Etz oseh pri *etz oseh pri*. The fruit
is just beginning to come to blossom. הוי אומר omer, זה ניסן
Nisan *Hevei omer ze Nissan*. It's ניסן Nisan *Nissan*. ואותו הפרק זמן
בהמה וחיה ועוף שמזדווגין זה עם זה *Ve'oto haperak zman behema vechaya
veof shemizdavjin ze im ze*, and that's the period of fertility. So
the other one mentioned rain, you know, here he's talking about yeah
but for the animals it's the spring that's a period of fertility.
שנאמר shene'emar, לבשו כרים הצאן *Shene'emar livshu charim hatzon*, which is the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* we quoted earlier, if you'll remember, which is why
the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah* for sheep and for מעשר
בהמה *ma'aser behema* is in אלול *Elul* or תשרי Tishrei, *Tishrei* because
they are mating in ניסן Nisan *Nissan*. So therefore it makes sense
that this time of fertility and you see through the ברכה bracha,
*bracha* of פרו ורבו *pru u'revu* and so on, although it's interesting
the פסוקים pesukim. *psukim* never speak of. but it makes sense to
associate that image of the creation of the world and the fecundity
of the world with this period of time in ניסן. Nisan, Okay.
ואידך נמי הכתיב עץ עשה פרי, Ve'idach nami haksiv etz oseh pri,
so what does רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer do with the verse that
says 'a tree that makes fruit', which sounds like it's not yet
filled with fruit, it's just that it is beginning to make fruit?
That sounds like ניסן. Nisan ההוא לברכה לדורות הוא דכתיב. Hahu libracha
ledoros hu dechtiv. No, that's to tell you in the future that
the trees are created with the potential to make fruit. This is
the blessing that they have for future generations. But when it was
originally created, it was filled with fruit. עץ עשה פרי etz oseh
pri means it has the capacity to make fruit, and that is
the nature of the tree. But the time was תשרי Tishrei and
when it was already filled with fruit. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says, ואידך נמי הכתיב עץ פרי. Ve'idach nami haksiv etz pri.
What does רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua do with the idea that it
says 'a fruit tree', which sounds like it's filled with fruit, sounds
like it's
תשרי? Tishrei ההוא כרבי יהושע בן לוי דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי
כל מעשה בראשית בקומתן נבראו, Hahu kerabbi Yehoshua ben Levi de'amar rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi kol ma'aseh bereishis bekomasan nivre'u, they were created already
in their full stature, right? It's not like, you know, when אדם
Adam and חוה Chava were created, they were one-day-old infants. Right? So
it's not when the trees were created, they were little—it was a
little sapling. Trees were created—you know, the things were created already fully
formed. לדעתן נבראו, Leda'atan nivre'u, now that's an interesting idea. They were—they
were created only with their acquiescence. You know? So God basically said
to the trees, 'Do you trees want to be created?' So besides
of the personification aspects there, or the anthropomorphism aspects—I shouldn't say
personification—anthropomorphism, there's also the circular problem: how do you say to the
tree 'Do you want to be created?' if the tree wasn't created
yet? So maybe it's like to the, you know, somehow the tree
power in the world? I have no idea what this means. Okay,
anyway, right, trees have souls. Anyway, it is—there is a powerful image,
though, about like the sense
of, like, you know, the—the world—you know—making this inanimate world and, you
know—I mean, you don't want to get to the point of being
like—what is that? Druidism or whatever? You know, the trees—the spirits—I'm not
saying that far, but to see an idea somehow that the whole
world has this, like, you know, power and potential to actualize its
own, you know—it's not just inanimate. But anyway.
Someone says something about Buddhism or something?
Oh, God, okay. Fine.
Still maybe in the idea of the form of tree, you know,
like the Platonists.
Plato has this even before—right, right, the Platonic—right,
coming into the physical world.
Right, right. You know when it gets into those whole issues like,
you know, about how the sun and the moon argue with God,
like who gets to be the bigger one, right? You know those
similar and—and the famous מדרש Midrash that רש"י Rashi quotes also about
עץ פרי עשה פרי, etz pri oseh pri, God wanted it, you
know, to—to taste—the bark to taste like the fruit, and it didn't
listen and it, you know. So this whole idea of like these
powers in the world and that the natural world has like will
is an interesting idea and in some ways a disturbing—very disturbing idea,
but provocative nonetheless. Okay. So it says, so לדעתן נבראו לצביונם נבראו,
Leda'atan nivre'u letzevyonan nivre'u, and according to their צביונם, tzevyonam, which רש"י
Rashi. sort of sounds like it means like their distinctive shape and
appearance—which is not exactly the same, but you know, as these other
things, but it basically means that things were—everything was created with its
own very distinctive appearance and
shape.
שנאמר ויכלו השמים
והארץ וכל צבאם,
Shene'emar vayichulu
hashamayim
veha'aretz vechol tzeva'am, all the host. אל תקרי
צבאם אלא לצביונם,
Al tikrei
tzeva'am ela letzevyonam,
their desire or their—their, you know, particular
distinctive shape or appearance. So what does it mean—so how does this
answer our question about עץ פרי? Because it answers it that עץ
עשה פרי etz oseh pri, might—if it just said עץ עשה פרי,
it might have indicated that they're not yet big enough and—and at
the size enough ready to bear fruit. So עץ פרי says that
they are fully a fruit tree, not meaning that they're filled with
fruit, but that the full size of a fruit tree and therefore
prepared to really be filled with fruit. But ultimately they were not
yet filled with fruit, it was ניסן Nissan? and it was still
in the stage of עשה פרי where the fruit was coming out.
Okay, so that's the debate about when the world was created.
רבי אליעזר אומר—now, Rabbi Eliezer omer רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, of
course, you know, if you just think about the imagery, the whole
idea of ניסן Nissan. and spring and birth is a sort of
more powerful imagery to think about at the time of the creation
of the world.
Okay. רבי אליעזר אומר מנין שבטשרי נולדו אבות? Rabbi Eliezer omer minayin
shebetishrei noldu avos? How do you know that the fathers were born
in תשרי? Tishrei שנאמר shene'emar,
because the verse says—born, in תשרי. Tishrei, The verse says... says ויקהלו
אל המלך שלמה כל איש ישראל בירח האיתנים בחג. vayikhalu el ha-Melekh
Shlomo kol ish Yisrael be-yerach ha-etanim ba-chag.
Okay,
so they all gathered to the King Solomon in the month of
איתנים Etanim in the חג. chag. So we've mentioned already that in
the תורה, Torah, the months are numbered, right? It says החודש הזה
לכם ראש חודשים, ha-chodesh ha-zeh lakhem rosh chodashim, so ניסן Nissan. is
one, אייר Iyar is two, and so on. In נביאים, Nevi'im, in
תנ"ך, Tanakh, before גלות, Golus, like in these פסוקים pesukim by שלמה,
Shlomo, you have a numbering of months, but you also have a
naming of months. And the naming of months though somehow seems to
be Hebrew names, right? It's only after the חורבן הבית Churban ha-Bayit
and in books like אסתר Esther and עזרא Ezra and נחמיה Nehemiah
that you have the Babylonian names of תשרי, Tishrei, חשון, Cheshvan, כסלו.
Kislev. So here by שלמה, Shlomo, you have naming of months but
more given Jewish names.
And let's try to see what those names mean. Okay, so this
is בחג, be-chag, this is סוכות, Sukkot, and it is the ירח
האיתנים. Yerach ha-Etanim. So what does the word איתנים Etanim mean? איתן
Etan normally means like strength. So let's take a look. ירח שנולדו
בו איתני עולם, Yerach she-noldu bo etanei olam,
the month that the strong ones of the world were born, meaning
the forefathers. מאי משמע דהאי איתן לישנא דתקיפי הוא? Mai mashma de-hai
etan lishna de-takifei hu?
Where do you get this idea that the word איתן Etan means
strong? כדכתיב, ke-dichtiv,
like the verse says, איתן מושבך ושים בסלע קינך. etan moshavakha ve-sim
basela kinecha. You know, your dwelling place is secure, is strong. ואומר,
ve-omer, שמעו הרים את
ריב ה', shimu harim et riv Hashem, hear o mountains the argument
of God, והאיתנים מוסדי ארץ, ve-ha-etanim mosedei aretz, and the איתנים, Etanim,
the foundations of the earth. ואומר, ve-omer, so anyway, so presumably they're
reading that as a פסוק pasuk where the second half parallels the
first half. So איתנים Etanim are now also identified with mountains. So
now we're not just going to say that איתן Etan is strong,
you know, the idea of strength connected with a foundation, but we're
even going to drive the idea home because of its being parallel
and equated with mountains. ואומר, ve-omer, the verse says, קול דודי הנה
זה בא מדלג על ההרים מקפץ על הגבעות. kol dodi hinei zeh
ba medaleg al he-harim mekapetz al ha-geva'ot.
So my beloved is coming, which is the time of
redemption, skipping over the mountains, jumping over the valleys. So מדלג על
ההרים medaleg al he-harim בזכות אבות, bizchut avot, by the merit of
the forefathers,
which are seen as mountains. מקפץ על הגבעות mekapetz al ha-geva'ot בזכות
אמהות, bizchut imahot, by the merit of the mothers.
And therefore again, okay, it's sort of like proving one מדרש Midrash
with another מדרש, Midrash, but from that פסוק pasuk we understand הרים
harim is forefathers, and another פסוק pasuk has איתן Etan with הרים.
harim. So therefore we have it as the forefathers. There's a word
I think interesting though about the imagery of the mountains being fathers
and the valleys or the, you know, being the mothers. First of
all, could be the idea before both of these points, again, this
imagery of like Mother Earth, of fertility and so on, which is
very feminine imagery, is connected here with the גבעות, geva'ot, with the
valleys, which tend to be the ones the places where are planted
and things grow. Also, one does sort of wonder again the idea
of like just the physical sense of like protrusion, you know, the
mountains stick out and the valleys lie low and are indented, so
presumably that has to do with that association of that imagery. Yes.
So you just said a minute ago about spring being the more
natural time of creation, but that's what the argument was, was the
world created sort of fully formed in the fall, you know, sort
of like grown already, or is it a developing thing, which is
spring?
Right,
so that's exactly the idea of בדעתן ובצביונם be-da'atan u-vi-tzivyornam and so
on. Although the גמרא Gemara quoted the בדעתן ובצביונם be-da'atan u-vi-tzivyornam for
the one that said spring, but yes, you're right. In a way,
you know, in a way you're right,
that is the question. It sort of is, it gets back to
the whole sense
about the humans, why the humans are planted on the earth. Do
you see the earth as this burgeoning fertility and you're supposed to
be sort of part of the growing and developing, or like לשמרה,
le-shomrah, you know,
you're preserving it's already fully formed. But it's interesting, you're right, the
different types of imagery that are evoked by thinking about the spring
or thinking about, you know, but it is funny even with the
idea that the fall is fully formed, but it's also the beginning
of the period where things start to die and to, you know.
Although on the other hand, you could argue the opposite. You could
argue that the fall is the beginning of human creativity because it's
when you begin the planting and when you begin actually, you know,
the things aren't just like naturally coming out, but you are the
human component in terms of bringing life and, you know, to the
earth's hub begins in the fall, which is why, one reason which
is the logic why תשרי Tishrei is one, you know, we have
these two models, תשרי Tishrei and ניסן, Nissan which are exactly that,
right? ניסן Nissan, is the natural sort
of birthing of the world and sprouting forth, but תשרי Tishrei. is
the beginning of the agricultural cycle. So very interesting, yes.
Or as he says, דווקא מהארץ davka me-ha-aretz and in בראשית, פרק
ב' בראשית, Perek Bet Bereishit,
everything sprouts from the ground, everything grows from the ground. Yeah, and
the people, we all come from soil. Right, all the animals sprout
from the
ground. Right.
On the other hand, you could say that that's the spot where
it says about it raining, which the גמרא Gemara associates with תשרי,
Tishrei, and it says ואדם אין לעבד את האדמה. ve'adam ayin la'avod
et ha'adamah. So the idea of עבודת אדמה avodat adamah is something
associated more with תשרי, Tishrei, not with, you know, plants. Well, right.
Right. So it's very interesting to think about the different types of
imageries that are come up thinking about that and also the human
component in that all sense of fertility and creation. Okay, yes.
So when they spoke about the will and desire to create as
distinct from the created, so I was reading in an אריה קפלן
Aryeh Kaplan about it. So the first point of creation is ה'
Hashem's will and desire to create.
So now it's being paralleled by those that are created to express
their own will. Right. Right. Yeah, you know, you're right. That's also
very powerful in terms of that whole idea of like partnership, you
know, which the תורה Torah is explicit in terms of the human
being, which are בצלם אלוקים betzelem Elokim and they're there to somehow,
you know, be partners with God and take God's charge. But if
you think about all of creation giving over their will, then the
entire creation is sort of partnering with God in the creation. That's
a very nice idea, very powerful idea. Okay, so that's how we
get it with that it means that they were born in תשרי
Tishrei, because of איתן. Eitan. So how about the other one? רבי
יהושע Rabi Yehoshua, אומר: מניין שבניסן נולדו אבות? Minayin shebeNissan noldu avot?
Where do you know that they were born in ניסן? Nissan שנאמר,
shenaemar, the verse says, another פסוק pasuk by שלמה Shlomo by the
building of the בית המקדש: Beit HaMikdash: ויהי בשמונים שנה וארבע מאות
שנה לצאת בני ישראל מארץ מצרים בשנה הרביעית בחודש זיו Vayehi bishmonim
shanah ve'arba me'ot shanah letzeit bnei Yisrael me'eretz Mitzrayim bashanah harevi'it bechodesh
Ziv in the month of זיו Ziv and the next two words
which it should have quoted, which is הוא החודש השני. hu hachodesh
hasheni. Okay, now we know that again the numbering of months is
from ניסן. Nissan, So חודש זיו Chodesh Ziv is אייר. Iyar. Okay,
so let's see how we get from זיו Ziv being אייר Iyar
to the forefathers being born in ניסן. Nissan, Okay, so it says
בירח שנולדו בו זיוותני עולם Byerach shenoldu bo zivtanei olam
in the month in which like the shining ones or the distinctive
ones of the world were born. Now it's a little bit of
a challenge because the luminaries, ah, excellent translation, the luminaries were created.
But the problem is is that of course this is הירח השני.
hayerech hasheni. So רש"י Rashi has to stretch a little and say
it means by the time we got to ירח השני, yerech hasheni,
they had already been born, which is a bit of a stretch.
So then רש"י Rashi: has another explanation, which is that, you know,
the idea of ניסן Nissan. is not only the month of ניסן,
Nissan, but it's also a way to describe תקופת ניסן, Tkufat Nissan,
right, which is like the spring equinox or, you know, the spring
season.
And therefore רש"י Rashi says that maybe it's called this month is
called זיוותני, zivtanei, you know, ירח זיו yerach Ziv because תקופת ניסן,
Tkufat Nissan, the season, extends into אייר. Iyar. But it's a little
bit of a challenge. We're trying to use the word זיו Ziv
to identify it as ניסן Nissan, when the תורה Torah is explicit
that this is referring to the second month, which is אייר. Iyar.
Okay. Okay. So anyway, והכתיב בירח האיתנים. Vehaktiv byerach ha'Eitanim. Now what
do you do with the idea that it says ירח איתנים? yerach
Eitanim? If you say that they were born in ניסן, Nissan. what
else would ירח איתנים yerach Eitanim mean? התם דתקיפי במצוות. Hatam detkifi
bemitzvot.
No, that's because that period of תשרי Tishrei, is very strong in
מצוות. mitzvot. What does that mean? You look at רש"י. Rashi רש"י
Rashi says, a very nice short little רש"י: Rashi שופר יום כיפורים
וסוכה לולב וערבה וניסוך המים. shofar, Yom Kippurim, vesukkah, lulav, ve'aravah, venisuch
hamayim. And then also the ערבה, aravah, which is put in parentheses
maybe because that's a question of מנהג נביאים minhag nevi'im or something.
Anyway, so there's tons of מצוות mitzvot in תשרי. Tishrei. You don't
stop doing מצוות. mitzvot. So that's why it's called איתנים, Eitanim, but
not because that's when the forefathers were born. ואידך נמי הכתיב בחודש
זיו. Ve'idach nami haktiv bechodesh Ziv. Now if you say they were
born in תשרי, Tishrei, what do you do with the זיו Ziv
referring to אייר? Iyar? What would זיו Ziv mean if it doesn't
mean when the luminaries were born? ההוא דאית ביה זיווא לאילני. Hahu
de'it beih ziva le'ilanei. No, it means that the trees are blossoming
and there's like a glow, you know, a beauty around the trees,
and that's what זיו Ziv means. דאמר רב יהודה: De'amar Rav Yehuda:
האי מאן דנפיק ביומי ניסן. Hai man denafik beyomei Nissan. If you
go out in ניסן, Nissan, the reason of quoting רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda here is because of connecting, he's going to say a הלכה
halacha about a ברכה, bracha but connecting it with ניסן. Nissan. If
you go out in the time of ניסן, Nissan. in the springtime,
וחזי אילני דמלבלבי vechazei ilanei demelavlevei and you see a tree that
is beginning to blossom forth, אומר, you say: ברוך שלא חיסר מעולמו
כלום וברא בו בריות טובות ואילנות טובות להנאות בהן בני אדם. Baruch
shelo chisar me'olamo klum uvara bo briyot tovot ve'ilanot tovot lehanot bahen
bnei adam. Blessed is God who did not make lacking anything from
His world and created
goodly creatures and goodly
trees for human beings to derive pleasure from them, even from their
appearance, not only from eating from them. That's a special ברכה beracha,
you make when trees are blossoming.
Anywhere in the world or just in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? No,
anywhere.
Yeah. Yeah, you go look in your various סידורים, siddurim, it has
it. People that are aware of it, whenever it comes spring and
they walk outside, they're— where's a סידור siddur because I have to
remember remind myself, like what is that ברכה, beracha. you know, make?
So at the, let's do the store, they have a like flowering
cherry tree.
Oh yeah. Well, they used to. Oh yeah? Here's the ברכה. beracha
Yeah. I grew up in, you know, in Maryland, near Washington D.C.,
and then when there's the cherry blossoms, oh, that you can make
a ברכה for. Okay.
Anyway, alright. Anyway, so זיו Ziv means it's beautiful because the trees
are blossoming. Alright, so that's the question of when the forefathers minus
יצחק Yitzchak were born. Okay, now, מאן דאמר בניסן נולדו בניסן מתו.
man d'amar be'Nissan noldu be'Nissan meitu.
Now, if you say they were born in ניסן, Nissan. they died
in ניסן. Nissan, מאן דאמר בתשרי נולדו בתשרי מתו. man d'amar be'Tishrei
noldu be'Tishrei meitu. If they were born in תשרי, Tishrei, they died
in תשרי, Tishrei, שנאמר, shenaemar, ויאמר אלהים, Vayomer Elohim, excuse me, ויאמר
עליהם, vayomer aleihem, בן מאה ועשרים שנה אנכי היום. ben me'ah ve'esrim
shana anochi hayom. משה Moshe said to them, I am 120 years
old today. So what does it mean היום? hayom? שאין תלמוד לומר
היום. she'ein talmud lomar hayom. What does it mean today? So ומה
תלמוד לומר היום? u'ma talmud lomar hayom? היום מלאו ימי ושנותי. hayom
malu yamai u'shenotai.
Today I am exactly 120 years old. My days and my years
are complete. ללמדך, le'lamedcha, to teach you שהקדוש ברוך הוא יושב וממלא
שנותיהם של צדיקים מיום ליום מחודש לחודש. she'Hakadosh Baruch Hu yoshev u'memale
shenoteihem shel tzaddikim miyom leyom me'chodesh le'chodesh.
God fills out the years of the צדיקים tzaddikim day to day
and month to month. Presumably, there's an idea that a person is
decreed to live a certain amount of time. So presumably that means
a like 20 years, it means, or not 20, 70 years, it
means that full amount of years. So if somebody dies on the
day they were born, they filled out their years. מלאו ימי ושנותי.
malu yamai u'shenotai.
The amount that was decreed were completely filled. שנאמר, She-ne'emar, את מספר
ימיך אמלא. et mispar yamecha amale.
I will fill the number of your days. So therefore, if they
were born in תשרי, Tishrei, they died in תשרי. Tishrei, Born in
ניסן, Nissan died in ניסן. Nisan. בפסח נולד יצחק. be'Pesach nolad Yitzchak.
Now everybody agrees יצחק Yitzchak was born in פסח. Pesach. מנלן? minalan?
Where do you get it from? כדכתיב, kedichtiv, למועד אשוב אליך. lamo'ed
ashuv eleicha.
The מלאכים malachim say to שרה, Sarah, I will return to you,
or God says I will return to you at this time, מועד.
mo'ed. Now presumably למועד אשוב אליך lamo'ed ashuv eleicha means this same
time next year. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara here is interpreting מועד
mo'ed to mean, I mean there's a long תוספות Tosafot tries to
figure out if this fits with other things, but anyway, the גמרא
Gemara is interpreting it to mean a יום טוב, Yom Tov, a
מועד. mo'ed. So the next יום טוב Yom Tov you're going to
have a child. Alright. How can you already have a child by
the next יום טוב? Yom Tov? Not enough time to get pregnant
and to give birth. So the גמרא Gemara says אימת קאי? eimat
kai? When is this happening? אילימא בפסח, ileima be'Pesach, if they're telling
her this at פסח, Pesach, וקאמר לה בעצרת, ve'ka'amar lah be'Atzeret,
you'll have a child by שבועות, Shavuot, בחמישים יומין מי קא ילדה?
be'chamishim yomin mi ka yalda?
How can you give birth in 50 days? אלא דקאי בעצרת וקאמר
לה בתשרי. ela de'kaei be'Atzeret ve'ka'amar lah be'Tishrei. Oh, it
must be that it was עצרת, Atzeret, so then they say what?
By סוכות Sukkot you'll have a baby? בחמישה ירחי מי קא ילדה?
be'chamisha yarchei mi ka yalda? You can't have a baby in five
months. אלא, ela, of course you all understand the anachronism here of
making the חגים chagim already existing at this time anyway, אלא דקאי
בחג, ela de'kaei be'Chag, it's at סוכות, Sukkot, וקאמר לה בניסן. ve'ka'amar
lah be'Nissan. Okay, you'll have it in ניסן. Nisan So you see
that
יצחק Yitzchak was born in ניסן. Nisan That would be the only
way you have at least six months. So the גמרא Gemara says,
one minute, ואכתי בשיתה ירחי מי קא ילדה? ve'akati be'shita yarchei mi
ka yalda?
So six months still isn't enough. Okay. תניא. tanya. אותה שנה מעוברת
היתה. ota shana me'uberet hayta.
It was a leap year. Oh, so they had seven months from
סוכות Sukkot till ניסן, Nisan, and in seven full months, געזונטהייט, gesundheit,
you can actually have a baby. So the גמרא Gemara says מעוברת
היתה, me'uberet hayta, סוף סוף, sof sof, nevertheless, כי מדלי מר יומי
טומאה בצרי להו? ki madli mar yomei tum'a batzrei le'hu?
If you wait the days after שרה'ס Sarah's became impure, then you'll
be left with, then it won't be a full seven months because,
again, if you read רש"י Rashi on the תורה, Torah, you have
this woven into the story, right? You know, it says אחרי בלתי
היתה לי עדנה, acharei beloti hayta li edna,
right,
so I'll be having a youth. רש"י Rashi says אותו יום פירסה
שרה נדה. oto yom pirsa Sarah niddah. That day when the, you
know, when the מלאכים malachim came, שרה Sarah had menstruated. And that's
why also it says that he didn't feed her, he didn't feed
the מלאכים malachim with dough because she became a נדה niddah when
she was making the dough, and you don't want to give the
guests טמא tamei food. Anyway, this is all part of the Midrashic
interpretation of these פסוקים. So if she became a נדה niddah that
day, then she could not conceive. I mean, presumably they were keeping
הלכות נדה. hilchos niddah. That's also the assumption. Maybe even without that
assumption, if that's her period, she can't conceive right after having her
period, so you had to wait like a week or two. So
it's not a full seven months. It would only be six and
a half months from the time they were able, she would be
able to conceive till the time she could give birth. So the
גמרא Gemara says no. אמר מר זוטרא, amar Mar Zutra, מר זוטרא
Mar Zutra says, אפילו מאן דאמר יולדת לתשעה אינה יולדת לקטועים, afilu
man d'amar yoledet letish'ah eina yoledet liktu'im,
even according to the one that says that when a woman goes
full term and she gives birth after nine months, it will not
be a partial month, it will be nine full months. Again, don't
know exactly what that means, obviously women give birth a little prematurely,
but okay. Nevertheless, יולדת לשבעה, yoledet leshiv'ah, when we say a woman
gives birth... seventh month, יולדת למקוטעין yoledet le-mikutaim can be partial months.
So therefore it can be into the seventh month, you can still
give birth, again this is quite bizarre, you know, serious, right, serious
premature, right, you know, three months, two and a half months premature,
this was before they had incubators. And again, you know, this is
גמרא Gemara that assumes seventh month baby is better than an eighth
month baby. But nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara, does this a number of
times and assumes that there could be a birth just at the
beginning of the seventh month. So therefore, the only way this is
possible is from from סוכות Sukkot till פסח. Pesach. If it was
a leap year, that's seven months minus a few days for שרה
Sarah to get to become to be able to get pregnant, and
therefore it's that's how יצחק Yitzchak could be born by the next
מועד, moed, and that's how you see that יצחק Yitzchak was born
on פסח. Pesach. Yes, שנאמר, well, let's just first introduce, as it
says ויהי לתקופת הימים, vayehi litkufat hayamim, and it was at you
know this is by חנה, Chanah, right? So is that right, by
חנה? Chanah? Yeah. So and it was after the seasons of time,
מיעוט תקופות שתיים, miut tkufot shtayim, the minimum of seasons is two,
so a season is three months, that's six months. ומיעוט ימים שניים,
umiut yamim shnayim, and the minimum of days is two, so after
six months and two days חנה Chanah gave birth. So you see
you can give birth after even in the beginning of the seventh
month, yes.
Immediately after the visit to אברהם Avraham and שרה Sarah where a
child is promised, the מלאכים malachim go to סדום, Sedom, and
לוט Lot bakes מצה matzah for them, right? And רש"י says that
they're that shows that it was פסח, Pesach, right?
So and רש"י also says למועד אשר אליך lamoed asher elecha means
באותו פרק בשנה הבאה, beoto perek bashanah habaah, which basically means the
same time next year.
Yes, at the next מועד. moed.
So that makes more sense. So that's what this תוספות Tosafot tries
to figure out, okay? But this גמרא Gemara seems to you know
seems to assume that this event happened in תשרי, Tishrei. which by
the way would also fit with the next line, which is that
שרה Sarah was remembered in תשרי, Tishrei. right? בראש השנה נפקדה שרה,
be-Rosh Hashanah nifkedah Sarah, okay, so let's take a look. So it
says בראש השנה, be-Rosh Hashanah, okay,
בראש השנה נפקדה שרה רחל וחנה, be-Rosh Hashanah nifkedah Sarah Rachel ve-Chanah,
שרה, Sarah, רחל, Rachel, and חנה, Chanah, we just mentioned already שרה,
Sarah, right? So שרה, Sarah, רחל, Rachel, and חנה Chanah were remembered.
מנלן, minalan, where do you know this from? אמר רבי אליעזר בראש
השנה, amar Rabi Eliezer be-Rosh Hashanah, and everybody agrees to that, even
if you're normally a ניסן Nisan man like רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua,
right? ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is the time of remembrance, שנאמר, אתיא
פקידה פקידה, atya pkida pkida, and this is going to be really
underscored that idea of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah? as the time when
God remembers. אתיא זכירה זכירה, atya zchira zchira, you learn out from
the idea of to visit which means to remember and from two
words of פקידה pkidah and then from two words of זכירה. zchira.
כתיב ברחל, ktiv be-Rachel, it says by רחל, Rachel,
ויזכור אלקים את רחל, vayizkor Elokim et Rachel, God remembered רחל, Rachel,
ויפתח את רחמה. vayiftach et rachmah. וכתיב בחנה, u-ktiv be-Chanah,
ויזכרה ה', vayizkerah Hashem, God remembered her. Okay, now how do you
know it was ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah, So so
מאתיא זכירה זכירה מראש השנה, mi-atya zchira zchira mi-Rosh Hashanah, דכתיב, d'chtiv,
שבתון זכרון תרועה, shabbaton zichron truah, a day of rest, a remembrance
of the שופר shofar blast. So the idea of זכרון, zikaron, a
day of remembrance, right, is the central theme of ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah. and if God is remembering רחל Rachel and חנה, Chanah, he's
remembering them on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah, And now now that we
get that by רחל Rachel and חנה, Chanah, so פקידה פקידה, pkida
pkida, כתיב, now we're going to link that to a word of
פקידה pkidah and get it to apply to שרה. Sarah. כתיב בחנה,
ktiv be-Chanah, כי פקד ה' את חנה, ki pakad Hashem et Chanah,
God remembered חנה, Chanah, וכתיב בשרה, u-ktiv be-Sarah, וה' פקד את שרה,
va-Hashem pakad et Sarah, God remembered or visited שרה. Sarah. So the
same way חנה Chanah was ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah. שרה Sarah was
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Of course, there's a little bit of a
problem because we just said that the מלאכים malachim visited on סוכות
Sukkot and she gave birth on פסח. Pesach. So on the one
hand, you could have just said from that previous thing we can
figure out that she was remembered in
תשרי, Tishrei, fine. But now, not just in תשרי, Tishrei, we're saying
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah, So she remembered in ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
then how does that fit with the thing we just said a
minute ago, which is the מלאכים malachim visited in סוכות, Sukkot, right?
So it's not really working so well together. It works better if
you say the מלאכים malachim visited by שרה, Sarah, it was on
פסח, Pesach, and they said next year at this time. And then
God could have remembered her six months later at ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah and then you could have her still after okay, six seven
months give birth, whatever, you know. Well, not seven and a half,
from ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. till סוכות Sukkot is till פסח Pesach
is six and a half.
To אדר, Adar,
right, once you add an אדר, Adar, right, it's seven and a
half. Right, so anyway, that would work very nicely, right? It doesn't
so it doesn't work with the previous גמרא, Gemara, but that could
work well. It ties in that they're saying a year from now,
then few six months later she's remembered, and then seven and a
half months later she gives birth.
Especially because the גמרא Gemara wants to read מועד moed as being
יום טוב, Yom Tov,
right,
and the next יום טוב, Yom Tov, right.
So that's what this
that's what this תוספות Tosafot tries to figure out, okay. Now, okay,
בראש השנה יצא יוסף מבית האסורים, be-Rosh Hashanah yatza Yosef mi-beit ha-asurim,
יוסף Yosef was freed from prison on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah מנלן,
minalan, דכתיב, d'chtiv, תקעו בחודש שופר, tiku bachodesh shofar, so again the
tie-in to you know to. ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, is a time
of remembrance, right? Because, you know, I mean the whole point about
יוסף Yosef being freed started from an idea of forgetting, right? He
says כי אם זכרתני אתך ki im zechartani itach and right, ולא
זכר שר המשקים את יוסף, velo zachar sar hamashkim es Yosef, he
didn't remember. So anyway, so again the theme of being remembered on
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah. and again tying into a פסוק pasuk specifically
about ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. דכתיב, Dechsiv, תקעו בחודש שופר בכסה ליום
חגנו, tik'u vachodesh shofar bakiseh liyom chageinu, כי חק לישראל הוא משפט
לאלהי יעקב. ki chok liyisrael hu mishpat lelohei yaakov. So we already
have said earlier that that's a פסוק pasuk about ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah And now, עדות ביהוסף שמו בצאתו על ארץ מצרים, eidus biyehosef
samo bitzeiso al eretz mitzrayim, a testimony by יוסף Yosef when he
went out over the land of Egypt. So you see the פסוקים
open with ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. and then they talk about יוסף
Yosef being brought to פרעה, Paroh, being whatever made master over Egypt,
and therefore that was also on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah By the
way, there's a very, you know, graphically interesting דף, daf, right? Because
it's got this הגה hagah at the top. You know, so that
is somebody that is writing, I don't know who exactly wrote it,
but it is a comment on תוספות, Tosafos, again, trying to figure
out this story of whether the angels came on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah. or, you know, on סוכות Sukkos time or on פסח Pesach
time. So after תוספות Tosafos discusses it, some commentator added his trying
to figure it all out. Of course the funny thing is, is
those who wrote the גמרא, Gemara right, you know, if you were
writing
it
like nowadays
with like footnotes or something, you
would have put this
הגה hagah at the bottom
of the page and the גמרא Gemara, sort
of
look
normal. Okay, the problem is that it was a הגה hagah that
was a sub, like, like a footnote to the תוספות, Tosafos, so
you wanted to put it, you know, right after the תוספות. Tosafos.
But it's, but it's just a very strange looking page. I don't
think there's another page in ש"ס Shas that looks like this, that
doesn't actually start with, you know, the רש"י תוספות Tosafos at the
first line, everything gets pushed down. Okay. Now, בראש השנה בטלה עבודה
מאבותינו במצרים. Berosh Hashanah batla avoda meavoseinu bemitzrayim. Everybody also agrees that
they were freed from work on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah So how
do you know? Again, ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. at the time when
there's some sense of, you know, remembrance and a beginning of a
redemption and so on. שנאמר, דכתיב הכא, dechsiv hacha, והוצאתי אתכם מתחת
סבלות מצרים, vehotzeisi eschem mitachas sivlos mitzrayim, I will take you out
from under the, you know, the bonds of Egypt, or I'm sorry,
the סבלות, sivlos, the burdens of Egypt, וכתיב התם, ucheshiv hasam, הסירותי
מסבל שכמו, hasirosi misevel shikmo, I have removed from him the burden
on his shoulders. That's again from the פסוק pasuk of תקעו בחודש
שופר. tik'u vachodesh shofar. So the same phrase of להסיר lehasir to
remove the סבל, sevel, the burden, right, is, you know, that word
סבל sevel connects to freedom from slavery in Egypt. So that already
began on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Yes.
I'd like to,
I'd like to ask you about a theological idea about זכירה, zechira,
like it can't be that like God like had amnesia. Like when
we say זכר למעשה בראשית zecher lema'aseh bereishis and שבת, Shabbat, it's
really like an reenactment of a moment, like bringing a primal moment
into action. So maybe זכירה zechira here means something moved God to
intervene directly as it were. Yes, no, I certainly, the whole, yes,
the whole, I mean everything, almost everything about God is anthropomorphic, you
know, or anthropopathic, but זכירה zechira like when it says ותעל שועתם
אל האלהים מן העבודה
ויזכר אלהים את בריתו.
vatala shavasam el haelokim min
haavoda vayizkor elokim es briso.
It means God is choosing to to act, intervene, and to act.
Clearly, of course you could say what does that mean that God
is choosing and is that itself anthropomorphic? But yes. Come back to
deal with that. Right. Right. Yes, but these ideas of God remembering
or even the word פקידה, pekida, to visit, it's not to remember
which we associate with a, which we associate with an idea of
recollecting. Right, so even the idea of פקידה pekida is to act
on it and I want to say something even about the idea
of
זכירה, zechira, you know when
the גמרא Gemara says like, like זכור את יום השבת zachor es
yom hashabat or זכור zachor you know it says זכור zachor is
בפה. bapeh. Right and even in the גמרא, Gemara you know, you
know even when it relates to humans, so many things are really
referring to not inside cognitive or emotional but a way of create
a commemoration for, or you know, so even the word, yes, in
general like you know people have said somebody said Nachum Sarna עליו
השלום alav hashalom said to me like you know in Semitic cultures,
you know the idea like to thank somebody doesn't mean to thank
if you, you know, thank you know you praise them and you
do, you know don't say thank you. Everything, all these verbs which
we sort of translate as emotive or cognitive are really are, you
know are to be seen as as performing actions that demonstrate these
types of things. So זכירה, zechira, right, certainly by God but even
by humans could mean to do something to show or remembrance and
to commemorate. Yes. Dave, did you say there's a note here the
difference between זכירה zechira and פקידה? pekida? Yes, it says here so
זכירה zechira is to keep something in mind and memory but פקידה
pekida is actually to act upon it. Right. Very good. Yes. You
know, but I think what's-his-name makes that point, ירושלמי Yerushalmi makes that
point. the book זכור, Zachor, which is about the primary focus of
that book is the difference between memory and history. You know, what
do we choose to remember and the power that it has and
the story that we tell as opposed to just the facts that
occur. Jews were very good at memory, they were not historians. You
know, but memory was major, everything is זכור Zachor and זכור Zachor
and so on. But I do think that the point he also
makes there is about how זכור Zachor is translated as a sense
of doing something, to commemorate, to ritualize the זכירה, Zechirah, right, and
to do something as an act of זכירה. Zechirah. Okay, so now
it says like this, okay, moving on, okay, בניסן נגאלו, B'Nisan Nigalu,
how they were redeemed in ניסן. Nisan כניסא, K'nisa, אל it says,
you know, as we know, so okay, we don't have to say
anything about that. It's clear they were redeemed in ניסן, Nisan. that's
פסח. Pesach. All right, בתשרי עתידין ליגאל. B'Tishrei Atidin L'iga'el. Moving on.
Okay, now they will now we have back to the debate of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua when will be
the future redemption? So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says תשרי, Tishrei? אתיא
שופר שופר, asya shofar shofar, you make a link between the words
שופר. shofar. כתיב הכא תקעו בחדש שופר, Ksiv hacha tik'u bachodesh shofar,
blow on the on the month a שופר, shofar, which we know
is talking about ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah, וכתיב התם U'ksiv hasham and
it says about a Messianic vision, ביום ההוא יתקע בשופר גדול, bayom
hahu yitaka b'shofar gadol, which is a פסוק pasuk? that we say
in שופרות, Shofrot, the blowing of a שופר, shofar, it's a blowing
of freedom, right, and you know, יובל Yovel you blow the שופר,
shofar, it's also could have mentioned that, that's also right around you
know in תשרי. Tishrei But it's the blowing of the שופר shofar
represents freedom and that's the future redemption and that will also be
on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah. the same way we blow the שופר
shofar on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah, I mean it won't be on
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, it will be in תשרי. Tishrei, רבי יהושע
אומר בניסן נגאלו בניסן עתידין ליגאל. Rabbi Yehoshua omer B'Nisan nigalu B'Nisan
atidin l'iga'el. In ניסן Nisan? they were redeemed, in ניסן Nisan. will
they will future be redeemed. מנלן? Minalan? How do you know it?
אמר קרא ליל שמורים. Amar kra: Leil shimurim. A day of a
night of remembrance. ליל המשומר ובא מששת ימי Leil hamshumar u'va m'sheshet
yemei or- a night of protection. It's interesting question how you read
that. Normally you'd say somehow it's a night of protection, but here's-
here is how he is going to read it: ליל המשומר ובא
מששת ימי בראשית. Leil hamshumar u'va m'sheshet yemei bereishit. A night that
is protected and waiting and anticipated for from the very beginning of
creation, this is the special night. This was the night of the
first redemption and this will be the night of the future redemption.
ואידך, Ve'idach, and the one who disagrees and says that it won't
happen in ניסן, Nisan it'll happen in תשרי, Tishrei what do you
do with this פסוק? pasuk לילה המשומר מן המזיקין. Laila hamshumar min
hamazikin. It's
a day that is protected from the from the demons, which by
the way is from like you know, ולא יתן המשחית לבוא אל
בתיכם לנגוף, v'lo yiten hamashchit lavo el bateichem lingof, very much associated
with קרבן פסח Korban Pesach being protected from the evil forces and
so on. Interestingly, it didn't ask what רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua does
with the פסוק about שופר שופר, shofar shofar, which is pretty powerful.
I have to say also again the imagery is a good question
like I think this to me, you know, is provocative because first
of all, if ניסן Nisan, was the month of the initial redemption,
and it's ראשון הוא לכם לחדשי השנה, rishon hu lachem l'chodshei hashanah,
the whole idea is that now you start counting from ניסן Nisan
and this marks God's intervention and this is, you know, this indicates
this is the month of גאולה. Geulah. It stands to reason that
the future redemption will also be in ניסן. Nisan, Right, and the-
and also the imagery or, you know, about a world of rebirthing,
you know, you go from the dead of winter to the birth
of, you know, of the spring, it's very powerful as a period
of redemption. So the one who says תשרי, Tishrei, you know, is-
I find it challenging, like why would it be that it would
not be a continuation of the earlier redemption which is ניסן? Nisan.
What does that mean that it's תשרי? Tishrei. And, you know, and-
so A it's just not parallel and B what's happening in the
world, you know, again in terms of the- in terms of the
season, is not a powerful imagery of redemption. So I really don't
know, you know, I mean obviously the answer seems to be, well
okay, but it's- but if תשרי Tishrei, is the time when God
acts in the world, or, you know, but I don't know, God
remembers, he judges on תשרי, Tishrei but he acts on ניסן. Nisan.
So I don't- I still don't get it.
Yeah. Agricultural imagery does suggest that תשרי Tishrei is the time of
partnership and human initiative and creativity, you have to start to initiate
or participate in a process. You have that potential idea.
I know, I know. But how is it different than the initial
one? The idea is supposed to be that the initial גאולה Geulah
was more God- I mean it's true, בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael were
just being שלעפד shlepped along.
They were- they were יצאו, yatzu, they were forced out.
And the future redemption will be one of greater partnership. Correct. That's
an interesting thought because often the thinking is that the future redemption
will bring us to like Messianic times and it'll be, you know,
it'll be all God. And so anyway it does present I think
an interesting challenge to think about what the message is behind that.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues. ואזדו לטעמייהו- Ve'azda l'tama what?
Oh we'll get to that at the end. Okay, ואזדו לטעמייהו, Ve'azda
l'tamaihu, they go according to their reasonings. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in
a ברייתא: Baraita: בשנת שש מאות שנה לחיי נח בחדש. Bishnat shesh
me'ot shana l'chayei Noach bachodesh. Okay, so the מבול Mabul. *mabul* began
in the second month on the seventeenth of the month. So what
second month was it? Rabbi יהושע אומר *Yehoshua omer*, אותו יום י"ז
באייר היה *oso yom Yud Zayin b'Iyar haya*. That was the 17th
of אייר Iyar. *Iyar*, so you see Rabbi יהושע *Yehoshua*'s counting from
ניסן Nisan, *Nissan*. יום שמזל כימה Kima שוקע ביום *yom she'mazal Kima
shokeia bayom*. It is the day when the astronomical constellation
כימה Kima, *Kima*,
which רש"י *Rashi* says is the tail of the sheep. What's the
sheep? Aries. And what's the tail of Aries? Anybody know? How does
it translate that, sorry, כימה Kima *Kima*? He doesn't translate it, but
he says it's the Pleiades. Pleiades, which is the tail of Aries?
And it is the tail of Aries. Okay, so here let me
tell you... what? I think in the head of Taurus.
In the head of Taurus. Okay, so רש"י *Rashi* here if you
want
to know about your constellations, if you're gonna
take a look at רש"י *Rashi*...
where is the רש"י *Rashi*?
Okay, so רש"י *Rashi*, it is one, two, three, four, five lines
down
in the wide lines, and רש"י *Rashi* says, or the end of
the fourth line, וזה סדרן *v'zeh sidran*, טלה *Taleh*, שור *Shor*, תאומים
*Teomim*, סרטן *Sartan*, אריה *Aryeh*, right? So what's אריה *Aryeh*? Leo? בתולה
*Besula*, Virgo, okay. מאזניים *Moznayim*, the scale,
Libra. עקרב *Akrav* is Scorpio. קשת *Keshes*,
Sagittarius, okay, because of the archer. גדי *Gedi*, oh yeah, the goat,
Capricorn. דלי *Deli*, which is the water carrier, which is Aquarius. ודגים
*v'Dagim* is Pisces. Okay. וסימנך הטש"ף א"ב מעק"ט גד"ד *v'simancha Hatshaf Av
Maakt-Gadad*. And basically the way it works is, so you have it
like here, הטש"ף *Hatshaf*... okay, this is the fact, no foreign culture
ever penetrated the Jewish culture... I hope this is not...
that's being recorded in third person...
מעק"ט גד"ד *Maakt-Gadad*. Okay, so this is the cycle, right? Taurus... no,
this is the ram... what's that we say, Aries, Taurus, I forget,
תאומים *Teomim*, Gemini, etc.
Okay, this is the
cycle, and what happens is is that during the day, you know
when they say so-and-so is in the ascendancy or whatever,
if there are
twelve of these, each one, they're like two hours between each one,
you know,
that's I don't know this is the concept.
So when the day begins, if this in ניסן Nisan
*Nissan*, it starts by ניסן *Nissan*.
We're gonna see we count the תקופות *tekufos* and we start off,
you know, our starting point is ניסן *Nissan* for everything. So Aries
is in the ascendancy for the first two hours, it's all turning
like a wheel, right? So the first two hours Aries is in
the ascendancy, the next two hours, you know at least, you know,
the שור *Shor* starts going up and so on and that's how
sort of everything rotates and that's for ניסן *Nissan*. For תשרי Tishrei,
*Tishrei*, it would be, you'd be six months later, right? So this
stuff would be on the top and that would be on the
bottom. Okay, so what is he saying? He says, יום שמזל כימה
Kima שוקע ביום *yom she'mazal Kima shokeia bayom*. So if it starts
this way in ניסן *Nissan*, so by אייר *Iyar*, right, when the
day begins, right, this has already risen, risen there, the day is
going to begin with the שור *Shor*, right? And this has already
gone down here. It's one month later, so this is how it
looks. So he says, for some reason this is called שוקע *shokeia*,
because since it's already has broke, you know, has begun to rise,
you look at all the rest of the period as it's in
its setting motion. I don't know why, for me, you would start
calling about setting by midday. Anyway, so since this in אייר *Iyar*
is setting, okay, יום שמזל כימה Kima, שוקע ביום ומעינות מתמעטים *yom
she'mazal Kima shokeia bayom umayanos mitmaatmiym*, and apparently in the spring the
underwater wellsprings are less rushing because, yeah, because you know I guess
the melting of the snows and whatever and all of the water
comes in the fall, right, by the spring it's they're drying up.
ומתוך ששינו מעשיהם u'mitoch she'shinu ma'aseihem *umitoch sheshinu maaseihem*, because they perverted
their ways, changed their ways, natural ways, you know, maybe referring to
the idea that they, you know, interbred, or at least that they
sinned. שינה הקדוש ברוך הוא עליהם מעשה בראשית shina ha'Kadosh Baruch Hu
aleihem ma'aseh Bereishit, *shina Hakadosh Baruch Hu aleihem maaseh bereishis*, God perverted
the normal ways of nature. והעלה מזל כימה ביום ve'he'ela mazal Kima
bayom *vehe'ela mazal Kima bayom*, and the כימה Kima *Kima* began its
ascendancy in the day, so it started the day, I again don't
know why it matters here... who sinned? The people of the מבול
Mabul. *mabul*. This was about the מבול Mabul, *mabul*. I forgot. Okay,
so so the כימה Kima *Kima*... so it started the day, again
I guess I don't know why it matters here but just, I'm
sorry, who's them? The people of the מבול. Mabul, Of the מבול.
Mabul Okay, so the כימה Kima started its ascendancy at the beginning
of the day as opposed to in its beginning to set. That's
so but now why is that significant? ונטל שני כוכבים מכימה, ve'natal
shenei kochavim mikima, God took two stars away from כימה, Kima, והביא
מבול לעולם, ve'heivi Mabul la'olam, and the world came to and flood
came to the world. Not exactly clear, like the stars are like
little plugs, you know, in the big water storehouse above. You remove
the stars and the water comes down. Some also want to say
that the גמרא Gemara understands that the stars of כימה are what
keeps the world cool. So by removing the stars, it brought like,
we're going to talk in a minute about the hot water and
it made it very hot and boiling. Simple idea, right? המבדיל בין
מים
למים מתחת
לרקיע,
ha'mavdil bein mayim
la'mayim mitachat
la'rakia, right? So somehow you remove those two stars and the plugs
get opened, exactly. Okay, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, now רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says,
באותו יום י"ז במרחשון
היה.
be'oto yom yud-zayin
be'Marcheshvan haya.
So again רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is demonstrating that he thinks that
the world was created in תשרי, so the counting of
the second month is going
to mean
חשוון.
Cheshvan יום שמזל כימה עולה ביום, yom she'mazal Kima ola bayom, so
that would be a
day when the כימה would begin during the day would be rising
from below,
okay, it would start the
day at its peak or something, anyway, and would
begin rising, go figure out what that is. ומעיינות מתגברים, u'mayanot mitgabrim,
and the underwater wellsprings are getting more and more powerful, right, because
of the melting snows. ומתוך ששינו מעשיהם and because they perverted their
ways, שינה shina? הקדוש ברוך הוא עליהם מעשה בראשית, God perverted the
ways of nature והעלה מזל mazal כימה ביום and brought up the
מזל of כימה, the constellation of כימה in the day ונטל שני
כוכבים והביא מבול לעולם ve'natal shenei kochavim ve'heivi Mabul la'olam and he
brought a מבול. Mabul Now the question is what does it mean
שינה? shina? We just said according to him if it's happening in
חשוון Cheshvan. that's exactly what happens, that כימה goes up in the
day and there's a lot of water in the underwater wellsprings. So
the גמרא's Gemara going to ask, so let's finish up this סוגיא,
sugya, get to the תשובה. teshuva. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, בשלמא לרבי יהושע היינו דכתיב שני, bishlama le'Rabbi Yehoshua hainu de'chtiv
sheni, according to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua I understand what it means
the second month, he says it's אייר. אלא לרבי אליעזר מאי שני?
ela le'Rabbi Eliezer mai sheni? What does it mean second month? Which
is a bizarre question because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is just counting
from תשרי. The second month means חשוון. So תוספות Tosafot says the
גמרא's Gemara assuming that even if you say the world was created
in תשרי, the months are counted from ניסן like when the תורה
Torah says החודש הזה לכם ראש חודשים, ha'chodesh hazeh lachem rosh chodashim,
which is strange because presumably, you know, one way of reading it
is that's the חידוש chidush of the תורה Torah that we're going
to start counting the months in a different way, not linked to
the beginning one. Anyway, that's what the גמרא says, why שני? sheni?
Is it structure of a מדרש midrash as a שני sheni meaning
שינה? shina, No, I don't think so, maybe, oh you're right, I
didn't pick that up. Maybe you're right, בחודש השני, bachodesh ha'sheni, שני
sheni and שינה, shina that's interesting, I didn't think, that's a nice
point. Okay, שני לדין, sheni ledin, know the second month from the
time that they were being judged, you know, maybe they were judged
that it was going to happen already in תשרי and we know
תשרי is a day of judgment and so on. Alright, that was
a strange question. בשלמא לרבי יהושע היינו דשינה, bishlama le'Rabbi Yehoshua hainu
de'shina, so I think Dov is right that the idea of שינה
עליהם הקדוש ברוך הוא, shina aleihem ha'Kadosh Baruch Hu, שינה עליהם הקדוש
ברוך הוא shina aleihem ha'Kadosh Baruch Hu is because it's החודש השני.
ha'chodesh ha'sheni. I think that's very, I think you're, I think that's
totally right. So according to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua. we understand שינה
shina? because כימה normally starts descending and there's not a lot of
water. אלא לרבי אליעזר מאי שינה? ela le'Rabbi Eliezer mai shina? What
does it mean שינה? shina. What was different about it? כדרב חסדא,
ki'de'Rav Chisda, like רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. דאמר רב חסדא, de'amar Rav
Chisda, ברותחין קלקלו, be'rotchin kilkelu, they sinned with boiling liquid, which means
semen, okay, so basically referring to again interspecies breeding, interspecies sex, וברותחין
נידונו u've'rotchin nidonu and they were judged with boiling hot water. ברותחין
קלקלו בעבירה be'rotchin kilkelu ba'aveira in the sin, which normally just by
itself means sex, sexual sin, וברותחין נידונו. u've'rotchin nidonu. כתיב הכא וישוכו
המים, ktiv hacha va'yashochu ha'mayim, the waters abated, וכתיב התם וחמת המלך
שככה, ve'chtiv hatam ve'chamat ha'melech shachacha, the king's anger abated, so you
and חמה cheima is like fiery anger, so it means it means
not only abated but it means like the temperature got lowered, right,
it cooled off. So you see they were judged in hot water
and that was the שינה. shina The שינה was not that it
was כימה, not that it was water, all that was natural, but
that it was boiling hot. Okay, now we finally get to the
resolution. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, חכמי ישראל, chachmei Yisrael, the sages of
Israel מונין למבול כרבי אליעזר, monin la'Mabul ke'Rabbi Eliezer, they count from
the מבול, interestingly like, you know, what they're using our חומש. Chumash.
Anyway, they count the world, the מבול, the natural calendar like רבי
אליעזר ולתקופה כרבי יהושע. u'le'tkufa ke'Rabbi Yehoshua. But for the תקופה, tkufa,
for the seasons like רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua Now רש"י and תוספות
Tosafot both say if you're counting the seasons by ניסן, the way
you count the seasons demonstrates when you think the world was created
because presumably your point of reference is the moment of creation of
the world. That would be your point of reference and then from
that you know is it how many you know you figure out
how distant it is and you do all your calculations from that
point of reference. So if they're counting from the תקופה tkufa for
רבי יהושע they basically פסקן paskan בניסן נברא העולם. be'Nisan nivra ha'olam.
They just think that maybe the calendar in the תורה Torah is
from תשרי, but still they rule, they're presumably assuming ניסן נברא העולם.
Nisan nivra ha'olam. And חכמי אומות העולם, Chachmei Umot Ha'olam, oh, I'm
sorry, but חכמי ישראל—I Chachmei Yisrael was already jumping to the next
thing if what I said before didn't make sense. חכמי ישראל Chachmei
Yisrael make sense; they're פסקנ-ינג, paskin-ing, whatever. But now, חכמי אומות העולם,
Chachmei Umot Ha'olam, but the the the sages of the of the
world, מונים אף הם כרבי יהושע. monim af hem k'Rabbi Yehoshua. They're
consistent, and they think not only is the world created in ניסן
and they figure out the calendar from ניסן, but even when they
look at the dates in the תורה—again, Torah what the חכמי אומות
העולם Chachmei Umot Ha'olam are doing looking at the dates in the
תורה—they Torah assume that it's being counted from ניסן. So the interesting
thing here is is that everybody, forgetting on how you just read
the dating by the מבול—right, that's the only dating you have in
the תורה Torah until the story of יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim is
the מבול—but besides the question of the dating in the תורה, Torah,
everybody agrees that the world was created in ניסן. The גמרא is
going to say in the future that the fact that we say
in our liturgy זה היום הרת עולם, zeh hayom haras olam, you
know, זה היום תחלת מעשיך zeh hayom techilas ma'asecha shows that we
are assuming that בתשרי נברא העולם. beTishrei nivra ha'olam. So the so
David, back to your question, how do we rule? It's not clear.
Okay. There still remains to be the way in all the people
like you know who all the sort of rabbinic literature on תקופה,
tekufah, on תקופה tekufah assumes ניסן, right? Assumes that the world was
created in ניסן and that we're going to use that as our
point of reference. And right. But the but the but you know
so much of our literature, especially around ראש השנה, assumes that בתשרי
נברא העולם, beTishrei nivra ha'olam, so we can continue to be conflicted
about that. All right.